{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man needed Archibald Roane to cast the tiebreaking vote to defeat John Sevier for commander of the Tennessee militia. A Scottish merchant and a marine who served under Edward Nicolls were the subject of a trial overseen by this man. This man defeated the forces of Menawa at a decisive defeat for the Red Stick Confederacy. That battle paved the way for this man’s capture of Pensacola. For ten points, name this American general in the War of 1812 and future U.S. president.",
      "answer": "Andrew Jackson A"
    },
    {
      "question": "These institutions were the object of efforts to preserve traditional mores through the Falloux Laws which extended the Guizot Laws. Leo Collard reversed many reforms made to private institutions of this type by Pierre Hamel’s Christian Social Party. Belgium underwent two political “wars” named after these institutions. These institutions were secularized through laicite by Jules Ferry in a series of 1880s laws. For ten points, name these institutions from which Catholic curricula were phased out.",
      "answer": [
        "Schools",
        "Catholic schools"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this area, Roland Burris cited pollution concerns when he sued a gun club founded by men like OscRar Mayer and Philip Wrigley. During a 1968 trial, Abbie Hoffman claimed that it would have been better if protests had been allowed in this area ten miles away from a Democratic Nominating Convention. Found in its city’s North Side along Lake Michigan, for ten points, name this largest public park in Chicago, named for a president buried some 200 miles to its southwest.",
      "answer": "Lincoln Park"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man appointed William Mann to head a division named for the inclusion of members from many states. This creator of the Rainbow Division spoke of the “fulfillment... of [his] boyish hopes and dreams” Din a speech describing a group of people who “just fade away.” This man gave the “Old Soldiers Never Die” speech 19 years after he defeated the Bonus Army. Relieved by Truman during the Korean War, this is, for ten points, what five-star general who led the Allied war effort in the Pacific?",
      "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this company was accused of violating the Sherman Act in 1969, it spent 13 years locked in the longest antitrust suit in history. A future CEO of this company claimed “we get paid for working with our heads,” inspiring this company’s motto “THINK.” This company’s largest research facility is named for its first CEO Thomas Watson, who also names this company’s A.I. system that was victorious on Jeopardy! For ten points, name this technology company nicknamed “Big Blue.”",
      "answer": [
        "IBM",
        "International Business Machines Corporation T"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Grey Wolves bombed the Erawan Shrine after people of this ethnicity were deported from Thailand. Rebiya Khan was accused of leading these people in a 2009 riot which was sparkedby allegations that men of this ethnicity raped two women. The Republic of East Turkestan is a proposed independent state for these people, who mostly live in a province governed from Urumqi. For ten points, name this F minority who live in the Xinjiang Autonomous Region of China.",
      "answer": "Uyghurs"
    },
    {
      "question": "An attempted assassination of this man while at 56 Hope Road is explored in A Brief History of Seven Killings by Marlon James. This musician joined People’s National Party leader Michael Manley and Manley’s political rival Edward Seaga at a 1978 Peace Concert. As a symbol of black resistance, this singer wrote a song about Black U.S. cavalry regiments titled “Buffalo Soldier.” Bunny Wailer and Peter A Tosh were bandmates of, for ten points, what Reggae artist of “One Love”?",
      "answer": "Bob Marley"
    },
    {
      "question": "A black woman gave this man a bouquet of flowers which he accepted while speaking at the Independent Order of Pole-Bearers Association. This man’s most decisive victory came against Samuel Sturgis at the Battle of Brice’s Crossroads. Lionel Booth’s interracial forces were massacred by this man at Fort Pillow. An organization founded by this man in Pulaski, Tennessee in 1868 named him Grand Wizard. For ten points, name this Confederate Civil War general who founded the Ku Klux Klan. R",
      "answer": "Nathan Bedford Forrest"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Fluxus artist from this country prompted audience members to cut away her clothing with scissors in Cut Piece. Many Infinity Rooms have been made by a polka dot-loving artist from this country. Annie Leibovitz photographed a performance artist from this country naked next to her husband hours before his assassination in 1980. For ten points, name this home country of Yayoi Kusama and the wife of John Lennon, Yoko Ono.",
      "answer": "Japan D"
    },
    {
      "question": "This king married a woman who had earlier been married to a knight named John Grey of Groby, who died at the Second Battle of St. Albans. Two of this man’s sons died mysterious deaths during the reign of his brother and became known as the Princes in the Tower. This husband of Elizabeth of Woodville defeated Henry VI at the Battle of Tewkesbury, bringing an end to the House of Lancaster. For ten points, name this king of the House of York, the elder brother of Richard III.",
      "answer": "Edward IV T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech in which this ruler exclaimed, “Gentlemen, let us have no dreams!” sparked the January Uprising in Poland. On the day of his death, this monFarch signed the Loris-Melikov Constitution, though his reactionary successor had it repealed. This monarch created local government councils known as zemstvos in his 1861 Emancipation Reform. For ten points, name this Russian Tsar who freed the serfs but was assassinated by the revolutionary group People’s Will.",
        "answer": [
          "Alexander II",
          "Alexander the Liberator"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Among Alexander II’s titles was “Grand Duke” of this Scandinavian region, a title held by the tsar after Russia won a namesake war in 1806. That region is now a modern nation. A",
        "answer": "Finland"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Argentine anarchist Severino Di Giovanni attempted to assassinate this man by blowing up his train. This man was put in charge of relief efforts following the Great Mississippi Flood. This man created “meatless Monday” and “wheatless Wednesdays” while head of the US Food Administration during World War One. This man won election to his highest office by promising a “chicken in every pot and a car in every garage” in a race against Al Smith. For ten points, name this president during the Great Depression.",
        "answer": "Herbert Clark Hoover R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Anarchist Severino Di Giovanni was executed in Argentina using this method. As of 2020, only Utah and Oklahoma legally allow this method of execution, although South Carolina is discussing its return.",
        "answer": [
          "Firing squad",
          "answers indicating being shot"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2006, this leader claimed that anyone supporting Aleksandr Milinkievich would face having their necks wrung “as one might a duck.” This man won a 1994 election over his country’s incumbent prime D minister Vyacheslav Kebich. Hugo Chavez once called this man’s country “a model social state.” This man once replied that it was “better to be a dictator” than to be gay when a German foreign minister referred to him as “Europe’s last dictator.” For ten points, name this longtime president of Belarus.",
        "answer": "Alexander Lukashenko"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lukashenko’s threatened violence during the 2006 election was not enough to stop ten thousand people from protesting on election night in this capital city of Belarus.",
        "answer": "Minsk T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The oldest known human remains found in this country belong to the Tabon Man, while the first Austronesians to land in this country arrived at the Batanes Islands. The Laguna Copperplate Inscription is the earliest known dated writing from this country. This country’s ancient “Jade Culture” is believed to have originated in Taiwan. Ancient ancestors of the Igorot people in this country built the Banaue Rice F Terraces. For ten points, name this southeast Asian archipelago.",
        "answer": "Republic of the Philippines"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the assassination of her husband, Benigno, and the People Power Revolution in 1986, this woman became President of the Philippines.",
        "answer": "Corazon Aquino A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man wrote that “[Bush] was rarely the voice of realism on the Iraq war” in his book The War Within. A 2003 leak supposedly made this man the first reporter to know that Valerie Plame worked for the CIA. FBI Associate Director Mark Felt was revealed to be the source reporting to this man under the alias “Deep Throat.” This man began reporting for the Washington Post in 1971 where he met Carl Bernstein. For ten points, name this man whose work led to Richard Nixon’s resignation.",
        "answer": "Bob Woodward"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2001, Bob Woodward received an award given annually to the “leading figure in the journalism indRustry” named for this legendary journalist who was the anchor of the CBS Evening News from 1963 to 1981.",
        "answer": "Walter Cronkite"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "For his gallantry during this operation, David Lord received a Victoria Cross after being shot down on a resupply mission. Stanislaw Sosabowski commanded Polish troops during this operation, where the XXX [thirty] Corps’s failure to relieve a force in time led to a disastrous battle at Arnhem. During this operation, the First Allied Airborne Army intended to capture bridges to open a British ground assault. D For ten points, named this Allied invasion in the Netherlands that failed to secure passage over the Rhine.",
        "answer": "Operation Market Garden"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The five most recent Victoria Crosses were received for valor demonstrated in this Asian nation during fighting against the Taliban.",
        "answer": "Islamic Republic of Afghanistan T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Panaetius, this philosopher wrote a treatise on moral obligation dedicated to his son, which he titled De Officis. This philosopher imitated Plato’s Republic in the dialogue De Re Publica, where he recounted Roman history and laws. This philosopher accused the title man of plotting to overthrow the senate in his Catiline Orations. This philosopher was assassinated after he wrote the Philippics. For ten F points, name this Roman orator and enemy of Mark Anthony.",
        "answer": "Marcus Tullius Cicero"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 14th century Renaissance in classical Roman culture is often attributed to the rediscovery of Cicero’s work by this Italian poet who is credited with creating the concept of the “Dark Ages.”",
        "answer": [
          "Petrarch",
          "Francesco Petrarca A"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Taxi driver Homer Nida was killed in this city by Roy Belton, who was later lynched. A riot in this city began after Dick Rowland was accused of assaulting elevator operator Sarah Page. A 2001 state commission’s study of that riot concluded that this city conspired with the white mob. During that riot in this city, the neighborhood of Greenwood, deemed “Black Wall Street,” was firebombed. For ten points, name this city, the site of a 1921 race riot in Oklahoma.",
        "answer": "Tulsa, Oklahoma"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the 1917 Tulsa Outrage, 17 people who worked for this organization were tarred and feathered byRthe KKK. This Socialist-leaning union included “Mother” Jones and “Big Bill” Haywood.",
        "answer": [
          "Industrial Workers of the World",
          "IWW,"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "The Ancestral Puebloans...",
      "prompt": "Name the the ancestral puebloans......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Were called “Anasazi,” or “ancient enemies,” by this Southwestern tribe, the largest in the US F",
          "answer": "Navajo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were the first known inhabitants of this geographical feature formed by the Colorado River",
          "answer": "Grand Canyon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Are the ancestors of the Ute, the Zuni, and this modern tribe from northeastern Arizona",
          "answer": [
            "Hopi",
            "Navajo A"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Have many ancestral dwellings still standing at this National Park",
          "answer": "Mesa Verde National Park"
        },
        {
          "question": "Were described in Collapse, a book by this author of Guns, Germs, and Steel",
          "answer": "Jared Diamond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Venerated this trickster figure, who is depicted as a humpbacked flute player",
          "answer": "Kokopelli R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used these underground chambers for decision-making and kachina rites",
          "answer": "Kivas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Are divided into periods like “Basketmaker II” by this classification system",
          "answer": "Pecos Classification D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Valois",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Dynasty that they succeeded after the death of Charles IV F",
          "answer": "Capetians"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who fought in the Italian Wars and was captured at the Battle of Pavia",
          "answer": "Francis I"
        },
        {
          "question": "War between France and England named for its duration",
          "answer": "Hundred Years War A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law that prevented female heirs from succeeding to the throne which allowed the accession of the Valois",
          "answer": [
            "Salic law",
            "Salian law"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "French Calvinists who fought the Catholic League in the Wars of Religion",
          "answer": "Huguenots"
        },
        {
          "question": "King known as the “Universal Spider” who seized Burgundy R",
          "answer": [
            "Louis XI",
            "Louis the Prudent"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Dauphin supported by Joan of Arc who oversaw the recapture of English territory in France",
          "answer": "Charles VII"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who was accidentally killed jousting while celebrating the end of the Italian Wars",
          "answer": "Henry II D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Arab-Israeli Conflicts",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Largest Israeli city whose control has been contested during many conflicts F",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Jewish day of atonement on which an Arab coalition launched a surprise attack in 1973",
          "answer": [
            "Yom Kippur",
            "Yom Kippur War"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that allied with Egypt to invade Israel during that conflict, led by the al-Assad family since 2000 A",
          "answer": "Syrian Arab Republic"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Prime Minister of Israel, in power during the first Arab-Israeli War",
          "answer": "David Ben-Gurion"
        },
        {
          "question": "American location where a peace treaty was signed between Israel and Egypt in 1978",
          "answer": [
            "Camp David",
            "Camp David Accords,",
            "Naval Support Facility Thurmont"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose nuclear facilites were bombed by Israel in Operation Opera. R",
          "answer": "Republic of Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name of a series of Palestinian protests against Israeli occupation from 1987 to 1993 and again in 2000",
          "answer": [
            "Intifada",
            "First Intifada",
            "Second Intifada"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After viewing the damage caused at Pearl Harbor, this man claimed “the Japanese language will be spoken only in hell.” The pFhrase “Hit hard, hit fast, hit often” was a popular U.S. (20 pts)",
        "Navy slogan that originated with this man. A message sent to this man that popularized the phrase “the world wonders” was sent after he fell for a trap set by the Northern Force that led this man to move Task Force 34 out of position. That message was sent by (10 pts)",
        "Chester Nimitz to this man during the Battle of Leyte Gulf. For ten points, name this U.S. Navy admiral during the Second World War, nicknamed “Bull.”"
      ],
      "answer": "William “Bull” Halsey Jr. A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man signed the Treaty of Durham after defeating a Scottish rebellion by David I at the Battle of the Standard. This man was captured by Robert of Gloucester at the Battle of Lincoln shortly after he had crossed the English Channel to take the throne after learning of William (20 pts)",
        "Adelin’s death in the White Ship Disaster. In exchange for peace, this ruler signed the Treaty of Winchester to allow (10 pts)",
        "Henry II, the son of his rival, to succeed him. For ten points, name this English king who fought with empress Matilda in the Anarchy, the only British ruler between the houses of Anjou and Normandy."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen of Blois R"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) William R. Cooper argued that this god was the primary inspiration for Jesus Christ. The Younger version of this god was depicted sucking his finger while the Elder version’s eyes were the sun and the moon. According to (20 pts)",
        "Macrobius’s Chronicon and the works of Epiphanius of Salamis, this god was worshiped during winter solstice festivals. A conflict with Egypt’s southern neighbors may have influenced this god’s conflict with his uncle (10 pts)",
        "Set, who had ripped this god’s father apart to usurp the throne. For ten points, name this falcon headed god of the sky, the son of Isis and Osiris. DANSWER: Horus (accept Her, accept Heru, accept Hor, accept Har) (4) The first British minister in this country was John Wilton who was deployed following the creation of the Trucial States. This country was shelled by the British East India Company in retaliation for piracy in 1821. This country’s Bani Khalid tribes were conquered by a coalition of the Emirate of Diriyah, (+) Oman, and the Ottoman Empire in the late 1700s. This country has been ruled by the House of Thani since 1868. In 2010, this country was chosen to be the first Arab country to host the (*) FIFA World Cup in 2022. For ten points, name this peninsular country where the state-owned Al Jazeera Media Network was founded."
      ],
      "answer": "State of Qatar T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The death of a king with this name prompted Paul Hindemith to compose his Trauermusik. Another composer wrote four anthems, including Zadok the Priest, for a king with this name. According to legend, a king with this name began a (20 pts)",
        "tradition by standing up during a movement of an oratorio. Another king with this name attended a F concert aboard a barge on the Thames River, the premiere of (10 pts)",
        "Water Music. For ten points, give this name of the monarch in attendance for Handel’s Messiah, a name shared by six British kings."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "George",
        "George V prior to “Zadok”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The instigator of this event suggested it was justified by a false flag attack on a radio station in Silesia, the Gleiwitz incident. This event was codenamed Operation White and featured ineffective cavalry charges on horseback against (20 pts)",
        "panzers. This event was A decided in its early days by the “Battle of the Border” and culminated with the Battle of Kock. The Katyn Forest massacre was perpetrated shortly after this event concluded. (10 pts)",
        "Germany and the Soviet Union split up the spoils of, for ten points, what aggressive action on September 1, 1939 that began World War Two?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Invasion of Poland",
        "September Campaign, 1939 Defensive War,",
        "Poland Campaign,",
        "other answers that indicate Poland being attacked by Germany"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A document drafted in this city called for a bicameral parliament divided into a House of RStates and a House of Commons. The May Uprisings arose as a campaign to recognize a document that had been drafted in this city’s (20 pts)",
        "St. Paul’s Church in the wake of the March Revolution. Jury trials for criminals and a constitutional monarchy led by Frederick William IV were among the provisions of that document created by this city’s (10 pts)",
        "namesake 1848 parliament that was the first freely elected parliament in Germany. For ten points, name this city located on the River Main [MINE]"
      ],
      "answer": "Frankfurt am Main, Germany D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The protagonist of this work is buried at Fort Adams after dying on board the USS Levant, aboard which he created a painting showing a bald eagle that has lightning “blazing from its beak.” The protagonist of this work is thought to have been inspired by the Ohio Democrat (20 pts)",
        "Clement Vallandigham, and the work itself was written to bolster Union support in the North. In this work, an accomplice of Aaron Burr named (10 pts)",
        "Philip Nolan is exiled to prevent him hearing about developments in the United States after 1807. For ten points, name this Edward Everett Hale short story about a figure banished from his homeland."
      ],
      "answer": "“The Man Without a Country” T"
    }
  ]
}